Guide to the Robin Magowan Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robin Magowan papers
1936-2015
YCAL MSS 612
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.42
(37 boxes)
Magowan, Robin
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 26 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 27, 35 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Biographical / Historical
Robin Magowan (b. 1936) is an American poet, memoirist, and travel writer. He studied at Exeter, Harvard (B. A.) and Columbia (M.A.) and Yale, where he earned a Ph.D. in Comparative Literature. He taught at the University of Washington, and the University of California, Berkeley. In 1986 he founded the journal Margin; he served as editor until 1990. He is the author of books in several genres, including: Lilac Cigarette in a Wish Cathedral, Memoirs of a Minotaur, And Other Voyages, Fabled Cities: Samarkand, Bukhara, Khiva, Kings of the Road Portrait of Racers and Racing, Birds in a Forest Swaying, and The Rim of Dawn. He is the nephew of poet James Merrill.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robin Magowan, 2012-2017.
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: April 2012 Acquisition; July 2014 Acquisition; February 2016 Acquisition; September 2016 Acquisition; February 2017 Acquisition.
Scope and Contents
The collecton consists of correspondence, writings, notebooks, printed material, audiovisual materials, electronic media, and other papers documenting the life and work of poet and writer Robin Magowan. Writings include manuscripts and typescripts of poems and prose, including drafts and corrected copies of Lilac Cigarette in a Wish Cathedral (University of South Carolina Press, 1998), Memoirs of a Minotaur (Story Line Press, 1999), and other works. Includes correspondence and other papers relating to Magowan's uncle, James Merrill.
American poetry -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 21st century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 21st century; Magowan, Robin; Merrill, James, 1926-1995
- April 2012 Acquisition, 1936-2011; 23.0; (30 boxes)
  - Publisher, family, and college correspondence; printed materials, 1949 - 2000s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and printed material, 1950s-1970s, 2000s (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, primarily from family, including Magowan's father, 1953-2002 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence from Magowan's mother and others, 1953-2002 (Box 4)
  - Photocopies of James Merrill correspondence from University of St. Louis, Missouri and elsewhere, 1960s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, printed material relating to art and gardening, and printed ephemera, 2000-2010 (Box 6)
  - Typescripts including Green Dizzy Screaming Sun-Abyss; Harvard graduation material, 1958-2000s (Box 7)
  - Publishing agreements, photographs, family genealogy, family correspondence, and typescripts including Maya Revisited, Paul Clouded, Lilac Cigarette in a Wish Cathedral, The Wanton Current, and others, 1958-2011 (Box 8)
  - Corrected typescripts for Lilac Cigarette in a Wish Cathedral and other writings, 1970s-1990s (Box 9)
  - Corrected typescripts and photocopies, 1970s-1990s (Box 10)
  - Photocopies of typescript of Maya Revisited and other works, clippings, 1970s-1990s (Box 11)
  - Typescripts for Fabled Cities of Central Asia, and other works, subject files, correspondence, wedding photograph, clippings, and a wooden box and coins, 1971-2010 (Box 12)
  - Photocopies of typescripts and other papers, 1980s-1990s (Box 13)
  - Photocopies of typescripts and other papers, 1980s-1990s (Box 13a)
  - Writings including Trinidad, Birds, Connecticut, A Robin's life, Collected Incongruities, and poems, 1980s-2000s (Box 14)
  - Writings, including poems, prose relating to gardening, and manuscript of autobiography ("The Minotaur"), 2000s (Box 15)
  - Typescripts including The Wanton Current and others, 2000s (Box 16)
  - Notebooks, astrological charts, baby book for Robert Anderson Magowan III, and master's thesis, 1936, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 17)
  - Notebooks, bachelor's thesis, address book, and writings, 1950s-1960s (Box 18)
  - Notebooks, travel notes, "The Dream Book," year book, poems, scrapbook, and journals, 1950s-1980s (Box 19)
  - Notebooks including poetry, diaries, Japan and central Asia travel notes, and translations; typescripts; manuscripts; postcard, 1950s-1980s (Box 20)
  - Notebooks kept in London and elsewhere, 1950s-1980s (Box 21)
  - Notebooks including drafts of poems and prose, clippings, typescripts, and college coursework, 1973-1987 (Box 22)
  - Notebooks, writings, including drafts of poems, typescripts, and clippings, 1980s (Box 23)
  - "Planters" notebook, undated (Box 24)
  - Printed materials, typescripts, manuscripts, and correspondence, 1960s-2000s (Box 25)
    Scope and Contents
    Printed materials include ephemera, newsletters, clippings, and James Merril materials. Typescripts and manuscripts include The Poems of Jeufre Rudel, Literary Criticism of Andre Gide, and A Different Person. Correspondence includes letters and postcards from Sonta Angelo, Micaela di Leonardo, Mark O'Brian, and others.
  - Planter's notebook, newspapers, Harvard graduation materials, 1958-2000s (Box 24)
  - Audiovisual materials, 1963-2007 (Box 26)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Robin Magowan. Poetry Program, 1965 February 19; 1; 00:32:59; Static can be heard on the audiotape reel. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399759)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile.
    - McGovern, N. W. Poets, undated; 1; 00:19:03 (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399767)
    - Robin Magowan. Poetry, 1963 October 20; 1; 00:29:48; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399775)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Jimmy? Dub #2, undated; 1; 00:31:13; Program begins abruptly. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399783)
    - Robin Magowan. KUSP, 1986 April 9; 1; 00:31:01; A high amount of hum and hiss can be heard on the tape. Static can also be heard. Right channel recorded at a lower level than the left channel throughout the tape. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399791)
    - Robin Magowan. Poetry Lecture, 2007 January 9; 1; 01:02:07; The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 26, Item barcode 39002091399809)
      A note with the audiocassette reads: Dear Robin and Juliet, I hope you enjoy this tape. With appreciation and affection, Helen.
  - Photocopies of Virgil Burnett correspondence with Robin Magowan, 1970s-1990s (Box 28)
  - Photocopies of Virgil Burnett correspondence with Robin Magowan, 1970s-1990s (Box 29)
- July 2014 Acquisition, 1970-2006; 1.33; (2 boxes)
  - Notebooks and manuscripts, 1970-2006 (Box 30)
  - Notebooks, 1986-1987; 1990 (Box 31)
- February 2016 Acquisition, 1945-2015; 1.5; (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1945-2007 (Box 32)
  - Drafts of poems and translations, 2012-2015 (Box 33)
- September 2016 Acquisition, circa 1990s-2016; 1.33; (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence, circa 1990s-2016 (Box 34)
  - Electronic media, 2011; 1 (Box 35)
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- February 2017 Acquisition, circa 2012; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Self portrait in the Rose Garden, typescript, circa 2012 (Box 36)